A Guide to the John Graves Simcoe Papers, ca. 1776-1806
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
John Graves Simcoe Papers, ca. 1776-1806.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 30.6
49 items.
John Graves Simcoe, 1752-1806.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1930.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm M-1552.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lt. Col. John Graves Simcoe (1752-1806) was commander of the Queen's Rangers in America during the Revolutionary War. Later, he served as the first lieutenant governor of Upper Canada.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of Lt. Col. John Graves Simcoe. Included are eighteen manuscript maps, many executed in watercolors, of military actions in Virginia; printed maps like those that also appear in Simcoe's book, A Journal of the Operation of the Queen's Rangers, (Exeter, 1787); diagram of the principal streets and buildings of Williamsburg, Va; a watercolor view of Yorktown, Va., during the siege; copies of letters regarding the book and political and military affairs; reminiscences and memorabilia on Simcoe and his father; and two watercolors of soldiers of the Queen's Rangers. The manuscript maps and drawings were probably made by a soldier under Simcoe's command.
Organization
These papers have been organized into 2 series. Series 1 contains correspondence, memoirs, watercolors, etc.; Series 2 consists of manuscript and printed maps.
Index Terms
Persons:
Simcoe, John Graves, 1752-1806.; Amherst, Jeffery Amherst, Baron, 1717-1797.; Clinton, Henry, Sir, 1738?- 1795.; Cornwallis, Charles Cornwallis, Marquis, 1738-1805.; Falladon, Charles Grey.; Howe, William Howe, Viscount, 1729-1814.; Simcoe, Elizabeth, 1762- 1850.; St. Vincent, John Jervis, Viscount, 1735- 1823.
Genre and Form Terms:
Manuscript Maps--Virginia--18th century.; Military Maps--Virginia--18th century.
Geographical Names:
United States-- History--Revolution, 1775- 1783-- Maps.; United States-- History--Revolution, 1775-1783--British forces.; Virginia--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Virginia--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Maps.; Williamsburg (Va.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Williamsburg (Va.)--Description and travel--Early works to 1800.; Yorktown (Va.)--History--Siege, 1781.
Contents List
- Correspondence and Papers, 1781-1806., 3 folders (25 items) (Box-folder 1-3)
  Includes correspondence, memoirs, watercolors, etc.
  Chronologically arranged.
  - [John Graves Simcoe] to [Sir William Howe], [1776-1777] (Folder 1)
  - Cornwallis, York, to Henry Clinton, 30 October 1781., Copy. (Folder 1)
  - J. G. Simcoe, Wolford Lodge, to General Grant, 2 December 1789. (Folder 1)
  - J. G. Simcoe, Wolford Lodge, to the Bishop of Lichfield, 2 December 1789. (Folder 1)
  - H. D. Vincent to [J. G. Simcoe], 12 August 1789. (Folder 1)
  - [Jeffery, Lord] Amherst, Montreal, to [J. G. Simcoe], 8 December 1789. (Folder 1)
  - C[harles] Grey, Falladon, to [J. G. Simcoe], 16 January 1790. (Folder 1)
  - List of names of people to whom Simcoe sent copies of his Journal of the Queen's Rangers, 1789-1790. (Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clipping, ca.3 September 1794. (Folder 1)
  - Mrs. [Elizabeth] Simcoe, York [Toronto], to Mrs. Hunt, 28 February 1796. (Folder 1)
  - J. G. Simcoe, Wolford Lodge, to Captain Mackham, Admiralty, 8 October 1800. (Folder 1)
  - J. G. Simcoe, Wolford Lodge, to William Walcot, 11 August 1804. (Folder 1)
  - Viscount Howick to Lord St. Vincent, 22 July 1806. (Folder 2)
  - Memorandum, 15-24 August 1806. (Folder 2)
    Concerns Simcoe's voyage to Portugal. Page 1, covering 15-19 August 1806, is on the verso of a sketch of Simcoe as Governor of Canada (#10 piece in this folder).
  - Memorandum re Simcoe's death, 1806. (Folder 2)
  - Lord Nelson to General Simcoe, 18 April 1803., Copy. (Folder 2)
  - Extract from the journal T. Bailey with an account of Simcoe's funeral, 1806. (Folder 2)
  - Reminiscences about Captain John Simcoe & Lieutenant General John Graves Simcoe by H. D. Simcoe, n.d., 2 p. (Folder 2)
  - Statement of H. Caldwell about John Graves Simcoe, May, 1803., 2 p. (Folder 2)
  - Extract from Mr. Redhead Yorkes weekly Political Review No. 23, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Memoir of John Graves Simcoe, n.d., 5 p. (Folder 2)
    Similar to the published memoir in the back of Simcoe's Journal, printed in New York by Bartlett & Welford, 1844.
  - Sketch of Simcoe as Governor of Canada, n.d., 2 p. (Folder 2)
    Verso of page one contains the first page of a memorandum re Simcoe's voyage to Portugal 15-19 August 1806.
  - Memoir of John Graves Simcoe, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Watercolor of the Queen's Rangers, by Captain Mundy, n.d., Mounted. (Folder 3)
  - Watercolor of a Rifleman of the Queen's Rangers, By Captain Mundy, n.d., Mounted. (Folder 3)
- Maps., 24 items.
  Includes manuscript and printed maps of military actions engaged in by the Queen's Rangers. All of the maps are of Virginia locations.
  - Maps and notes., 3 items. (Page I)
    - Map of New Kent County, Virginia.
    - Map of Gloucester County, Virginia.
    - List of locations on the New Kent County and Gloucester County maps.
  - Map: "Action at Spencer's Ordinary.", 2 copies. (Page II)
  - Map: "Action at Spencer's Ordinary.", Hand drawn map. (Page III)
  - Map: "Action at Spencer's Plantation seven miles from Williamsburg ...", 2 hand-drawn maps. (Page IV)
  - Maps of Great Bridge Post., 2 hand-drawn maps. (Page V)
    - Map: "Great Bridge on Elizabeth River, Virginia."
    - Map: "Plan of the post at Great Bridge, on the south branch of the Elizabeth River in Virginia ...", Hand-drawn map.
  - Maps: "Skirmish at Richmond, 5 January, 1781.", 1 hand-drawn and 1 printed map. (Page VI)
  - Map of the skirmish at Richmond. (Page VII)
    A sketch of the previous map.
  - Maps of Naval Action on the James River at Osburns., 2 hand-drawn maps. (Page VIII)
  - Map: "Affair at Osburns.", Hand-drawn and colored map. (Page IX)
  - Maps of the action at Williamsburg Landing., 2 hand-drawn colored maps. (Page X)
    - Map: "Rebels dislodged from Williamsburgh Landing."
    - Map of the action at Williamsburg Landing.
  - Map and sketch. (Page XI)
    - Map: "City of Williamsburg, Virginia."
      Sketch map of the principal buildings of Williamsburg.
    - Sketch showing a view of Yorktown from Gloucester.
      Shows several vessels at anchor.
  - Map: "Attack of the rebels under Gen'l at the Point of Fork.", Hand-drawn map. (Page XII)
    Shows the military action at Point of Fork on the James River. This is near Columbia, Va. where the Rivanna River enters the James River.
  - Map: "Point Fork, Virginia." (Page XIII)
    This is a larger map of the one above.
  - Map: "Sketch map of the Skirmish at Petersburg ..." 1784., Printed map. (Page XIV)
    Map by I. Hills, Published in London by Wm. Faden.
  - Maps., 9 maps mounted on one sheet. (Page XV)
    These maps illustrate the following battles: Osburn's, Kingsbridge, Burrell's, Spencer's Ordinary, Point of Fork, Richmond, North River, and Quintin's Bridge.